so hi everybody um thank you for uh joining this
week's uh magnet seminar um it's good to see
another great turnout of people we've got over 50
people uh already i'm sure there'll be a few more
uh jumping in uh last minute so for those who
um aren't too familiar with the magnet seminars
we have a 25 to 30 minute presentation so we just
kindly ask that you keep your microphones mediated
during the presentation if you do have any um
connection issues and turning off your your video
feed can also help to to improve um a connection
um at the end of the seminar we'll have chance for
a 10-15 minute um chit chat and discussion so we
welcome questions um either um um via video and
microphone but if you don't want to ask a question
yourself please just type it into the chat and um
either myself or or one of the other conveners
will read it out for you and as always most of
us are working at home in various forms of home
offices so if you do have to go halfway through
the seminars i just go it's not a problem there'll
be a recording made available on youtube uh later
on and at the very end of the seminar we have a
chance for a bit of social catch-up with everybody
um and none of that's recorded so it's a
bit of a free-for-all just to chit chat
and catch up with everybody um and so today
i'm really pleased to say that we have phil
livermore from uh university of leeds i just love
the road from us in liverpool and he's going to
be talking about uh rq intensity spikes in the
levant region so i will hand over to you phil
thank you and a very good
morning to you from leeds
can i just check that you can all see that
yeah great okay yes uh so uh i want to tell you
uh today about some some work that i've been uh
undertaking recently with my collaborators on
this eve gallery and alex fournier in paris
which is focused on understanding
archaeomagnetic intensity variations
in particular the proposed geomagnetic spikes in
the in the level and an alternative title to this
talk is really counting spikes in noisy data
which really gets to the heart of what i'm i'm
going to tell you about so the the story of
the geomagnetic spike starts about started
about a decade ago with the publication of of
several papers uh where the authors looked at at
several archemagnetic sites in the levant region
which includes modern day israel and jordan and
they they looked at slag deposits
which are waste deposits from iron age
copper smelting sites and in particular these
sites were very well stratified so the oldest
stuff at the top the most recent uh sorry the
oldest stuff at the bottom the most recent
at the top everything's very well layered uh and
because of this the authors were able to propose
a very tight sequential chronology uh based
on this on this a well-defined stratification
um and the authors analyzed various slag
and pottery samples for paleo intensity and
they also dated some of the layers using
carbon-14 analysis and what they found was
quite staggering and that was two two
proposed uh spikes in the geomagnetic field
uh one about 980 bc and one about 890.
uh so set up on a background of fairly uh
not quite sedate but fairly fairly low level
second variation these two spikes showed massive
intensity increases uh of about a factor of
a hundred percent only over a few decades
and in the intervening 10 years since since these
studies first came out uh whilst of course the
data set has uh has improved it's increased
in number has been updated been refined by
improved criteria for data selection nevertheless
there remains strong evidence of rapid change
um and the the essence of the talk
really is about how we construct a
a curve through the uh the the data set
um which is an expanded version of what
you see in front of you um and how we use
that to understand your magnetic spikes
so geomagnetic spikes occurred during what's
termed the levantine iron age anomaly which
was a a a a temporal high in the intensity uh here
you can see several global magnetic field models
plotted uh in amongst the individual
data uh localized to this region
so why is it important to understand these spikes
well crucially there's no historical or modern day
analog to to these these are the only uh these are
the only known occurrence of such rapid magnetic
field chains that we have and indeed if you look
at the typical rate of change of intensity uh
0.75 to about two and a half micro testers a
year this is somewhere between five and twenty
times the present day maximum rate of change
of intensity so there's definitely something
here to explain and understand spikes
are really difficult to reproduce in
in geodynamo models so there's there's
a gap in our in our understanding
to to make the magnetic or to to explain
magnetic field change we either need to
rely on one of one or both of two processes one
is advection of magnetic field and stretching
within earth's liquid core and the other is
diffusion of magnetic field from within the core
but it's true it it's it's the case that
such rapid intensity changes definitely challenges
our understanding of of of these processes so
either we need anonymously fast flows or
we need some form of abnormal emergence
of magnetic field from within the
core that can explain these features
so in order to um analyze this we we collected
all published archaeomagnetic data in the region
of 1200 to 500 bc which which roughly uh defines
the periods of geomagnetic spikes and these were
all reduced to palmeira in syria which was
roughly at the center point of the dataset
the the published archaeomagnetic data are
heterogeneous by which i mean they they either
refer to fragment level or thermal unit level
samples so for example a shard a brick or a kiln
or they refer to a group level average over some
number of fragments which are assumed to be of the
same age uh so in in the figure you can see the
the data set that we collected from the literature
and you can also see a global model which is the
sureq iron age model showing the general trend of
showing showing the the general trend
according to that model uh in the region
and you can see the discrepancy of the fragment
of of some of these uh of these samples um
extending way beyond the two
sigma error bounds of the model
most of the data i showed is fragment level
data and so for most of this presentation
i'm going to focus on this data set and
here we see all the fragment level samples
as a plotted with intensity and age
and and the the key question is what is the
intensity curve the variation of the intensity
with time that's consistent with this data set
and from that curve we can then assess the number
and the nature of of the geomagnetic spikes and
it's important that we have such a curve because
it's very hard otherwise to objectively assess
whether or not we've had rapid intensity change
as an example of that this is these are the data
points around 980 bc where one of the spikes were
proposed which seems to fit well with the data
set as shown in the in the figure here's here's
another of the spikes which are proposed
okay you might think that sound that that
looks uh all very convincing but the more
you look of course the more spikes you see
so here's here's some more data which look uh
look like i might define a spike and here's
some others and you can keep going and you see
the more you look you see spikes everywhere
so this is there's there probably aren't
so many spikes in this data set but we
need some way of up to objectively
assess uh what what what's going on
uh i mentioned the fragment data set uh but if
we look uh only at the data defined by averages
uh of of n data points that
seem to be of the same age
then then of course th there are much fewer
uh members of this data set and here they are
and i'll come back to these uh
towards the end of the presentation
so the key question is how do we fit a model
to these data the data are are non-uniform
in time so there are some times where
there are more uh more data than others
the data are uncertain intensity and the
uncertainties are different for each data point
the samples all have uncertainty in age and
some of the samples are age ordered specifically
those derived from the stratified data sets i i
introduced right at the start of the presentation
on the on the modeling side what kind of what
kind of properties and model might we want
well ideally we want a model that is as simple as
possible and you could say has a minimal curvature
that is required by the data we don't want to over
fit the data we want a simple model as possible
we'd also like a model that can handle rapid
variations at some times but steady variations
at other times so we'd like some kind of modeling
that can accommodate multiple time scales
and we'd also of course like to have some
handle on the uncertainty of any any model fit
so fitting fitting data or fitting model fits
through data is a very common practice in in
the geomagnetism community um and typically when
people construct job global geomagnetic models
rather than local models like
i'm going to talk about here
typically what people do is they introduce a
model and they then they smooth it using some
some form of of global penalization of complexity
the disadvantage with that is it doesn't really
allow for multiple time scales you typically
have a similar smoothing of the model everywhere
what i'm going to talk today
about is a new approach which is a
based on bayesian modeling which doesn't have any
explicit damping where the data self select times
where rapid change is needed and this
modeling process provides formal uncertainties
so bayesian methods are named after thomas bayes
who was an 18th century statistician after whom a
very famous famous bayes formula that you see in
front of you was named this formula relates the
what's term the posterior probability
which is the probability of a model
that's the thing we'd like given the data set d to
various things so the posterior probability is the
product of something called the likelihood here
which which is the probability of the data given
a model times a prior divided by a normalization
factor here which is the called the evidence
so what we'd like to find is the posterior
distribution of some time dependent models
given the data set now we can only really do this
numerically and so what we do is we create an
ensemble uh using something termed a monte carlo
markup chain process mcmc i describe that in it
i'll describe that briefly uh and when we create
the ensemble the models with higher probability
are sampled more often and we need some way
to characterize our model ensemble so the way
i'm going to describe this is by using the median
median bottle however of course we
have the full statistics of the model
so in terms of the model what do i mean well
the model is a piecewise linear fit through
through the data and a
whole bunch of unknowns here
the number of the interior vertices so the number
of linear segments of this of this linear fit
is unknown as are the position of the
interior vertices so in other words where the
the points at which the linear
segments to uh connect with each other
uh in our in our modeling process we also
allow the data ages to be found by the model
so the data ranges themselves are unknown and
we explore the model space using a random walk
any bayesian procedure needs to
define prior information which is the
information it's a it's a formulation of
our beliefs on the probability prior to the
introduction of any data and so we need to propose
some prior distributions on the number of vertices
and the age and intensity of each internal vertex
and we also need to impose a distribution of
on each data mage and all of these prior
distributions are are reasonable um and i'll
point you to the reference where you can look up
exactly what we've done at the end we also need to
we also need to have a or decide upon a likelihood
which we assume to be normally distributed
the method i'm going to talk about i'm describing
is is transdimensional which is a fancy word for
really saying that the number of model parameters
is also an unknown so in other words the number
of linear segments is not is not determined
by by the user it's determined by the data
themselves and there's no explicit regularization
there's no there's no dumping applied instead
we rely upon the natural uh the natural
nature of bayesian methods to be parsonal
parsimonious that is to to favor low
dimensional models uh above complex models
each model is a is a piecewise linear
fit but when you average them you get a
smooth evolution as i'll demonstrate shortly
okay so this modeling process uh we've
named age hyper parameter reverse jump
monte carlo markov chain it's a very long title
and i'll just break it down for you a little bit
so age hyper parameter means that the data
ages are part of the model so as part of
the statistics that we generate we all we we not
only derive the intensity evolution but we also
uh calculate the um the full statistics of all the
data ages as well reverse jump just means that the
algorithm algorithm can reverse up and down the
dimensionality of the system so that is we can
we can look for both simple and complex models and
traverse between them and then this bit at the end
the monte carlo markup chain basically means it's
an intelligent random walk through model space
so i just wanted to describe to you a few
a few results that accompanied the paper
that described this method uh a few years ago now
before we get on to the levantine uh dataset this
data set i'm showing you here we term paris 700.
it's a it's a data set of archaea intensity uh
samples all found within 700 kilometers of paris
you can see here plotted intensity against time
and we we're going to i'm going to show you what
happens when we apply this method through through
these data so this is what happens you can see the
the data set in front of you with the error bars
and i've characterized this distribution of models
which is the posterior distribution by the average
the median and the mode in different colors
and they pretty much over overlap each other
and you can see a measure of
uncertainty of this bayesian uh modeling
by the 95 percent credible intervals so
there's this there's a there's a few things
that are of note here firstly where the data
require complicated time dependence then the model
accommodates that by being by showing a very
strong time dependence for example you can see
there's very well resolved oscillations in
intensity however where the data do not require
complex time dependence uh none is none is
returned and and so you can see this very
simple constant fit through the intensity
because the data are simply happy
for that that is a consistent model and does
they don't require any additional complexity
and if you're interested you can find
this this modeling uh it's on github
i'm not going to give you a live demonstration
of it now but but the the model is actually
coded in fortran for speed and all you need
to do is if it is go to the github repository
download it compile it uh configure the input file
and then run the code and a typical ensemble size
of about 5 million ensemble members takes about a
minute on a laptop so it's very quick and you'll
also find the data sets and the python scripts
that generate all the figures i'll show today
so what happens when we apply this modeling
procedure to the levantine data set
well in this figure i showed you i'm showing you
the fragment level data set with the error bars
on intense intensity and age and
in purple you can see the median of
this uh on of this bayesian model fit to the data
and in the panel beneath beneath that
in in red you can see the rate of change
of of this median curve as a function of time
so as i said i i've i've showed you the original
fragment level data set to accompany this figure
but as i mentioned earlier the metal so the the
method also gives you statistics on the sample age
themselves and and so the method actually gives a
preferred age and intensity uh for each sample
okay and i'm going to show you what that looks
like now and so you can see that the the samples
move closer to the curve of course because they're
everything's trying to be consistent there are
locate there are some times where the samples
don't apparently seem to match the curve but of
course these samples are pulled uh to the left
and to the right so because i'm plotting the
median age as derived by this modeling process
the the ages lie in between the two branches
of the curve that's why they fall in the middle
okay so having found a a way of
fitting a curve through the data
set we'd like we're now likely trying
to characterize the geomagnetic spikes
and in order to do that we needed
to write down what a spike was
and so we proposed a number of
characteristics so the first of which
is that a geomagnetic spike represents a peak
in intensity and in particular exceeds the
neighboring minimum by five microtesla so in other
words it's a well pronounced peak in intensity
the second criteria is on the rate
of change and in particular a spike
must have a high rate of change and at some
point it exceeds the present day rate of change
which is about 0.12 testers a year and the
times at which this happens then defines the
width of the spike so we have some way of defining
when the spike starts and when and when it ends
and the spike also needs to
represent anomalously large
intensity variation which we take to
mean greater than 0.6 microteslas a year
and these definitions build upon other
other proposals in the literature um
one thing that's worth mentioning is that our
dash of the the definition of the spikes here
has no defined time scale so spikes could be 10
years long they could also be a hundred years long
so what happens when we apply our definition
of spikes then to the intensity variation curve
well we actually find six geomagnetic
spikes that are consistent with the data
according to the fragment
level uh data set and i've
i've drawn the duration of the spike uh
within within the blue boxes so six blue boxes
uh each defining a spike and each has a star
with a different color uh and so you can see
uh clearly where the where the center
points are the spikes are and their age
so importantly two of these spikes have already
been proposed in the literature but there are four
others which are new at least new in the sense
that they've not been spotted before but of course
this is all based upon existing data so these are
new spikes but discovered in the existing data set
and what can we say about the duration of
spikes well if we if we chop out the spikes
from the uh intensity variation curve and we
plot them on a centered age figure like this
so they're all stacked one on top of the other of
course they're all the six spikes all in different
colors we can we can very easily see uh how how
long the the spikes have have lasted and they vary
from the shortest spike of about 30 years which is
the yellow one uh right up to 100 years which is
the purple one and they're generally symmetric
in age but they're not necessarily for example
the blue the blue spike uh in the middle here
you can see is a little bit skewed to one side
uh i lastly want to say something very briefly
about the sensitivity of the of this conclusion
and of the geomagnetic spikes um so not 93 of the
139 data fragment level data contain very small
intensity errors which might be underestimates
of the of their true intensity error
and so what we can do is we can test
the sensitivity of this by sequentially
increasing the minimum intensity error from zero
uh up to three four five and six microteslas
so by increasing the error budget of course
what we might expect is that we can fit
another smoother curve through the data and
thereby the number of spikes would go down
so this is what we find if we impose a minimum
of three micro teslas intensity error uh
the six spikes reduced to five spikes but not
by an awful lot there used to be a spike here
at about 790 bc which only marginally doesn't
fulfill our criterion for being a spike
okay so it's it's all it's almost six spikes
so this this minimum of three microtesters
doesn't make an awful lot of difference to
our conclusions but as you start to increase
the intensity error budget our six spikes now
drop to four when we reach a five microtesla
threshold we we drop down now to one spike
and this is an interesting uh value for the
uncertainty in intensity because it's a level
of uncertainty considered by other authors
i'm also showing here in green the shawq iron
age model that is shown right at the start
which is beginning to look
quite similar to this smoother
intensity evolution and as we go up to six
microteslas uh we're now dropping we've now
dropped to zero spikes and the evolution now
very closely follows this shorku iron age model
i mentioned right at the start that there
was not only a fragment level data set for
the levantine region but the group level data set
which comprised averages over at least n fragments
assume dated at the same age these were the data
sets and what happens when we apply our analysis
to these well we don't see many spikes at all for
the for the group level uh data set consisting of
averages over at least two samples we find only
one spike um and if we increase the stringency
of the averaging to at least three fragments
we find no spikes these these data points are
are the posterior median intensity and
age so they're the the corresponding
data which is most consistent um
with with the intensity evolution
okay so it's going to wrap up here
so what i've talked about here is the area
of gym magnetic spikes and i think it gives
a really unique opportunity to study very rapid
intensity change uh i've briefly introduced
a bayesian method that's ideally suited to
characterizing rapid changes in intensity and
taken at face value the fragment level data set
appears to require six spikes which is a lot more
than than has been proposed so far in the
literature um and if you if you reassess
the data either by looking looking at the group
averaging or by increasing the error budget you
get a smoother variation and fewer spikes so the
real take home message here is that the levantine
dataset may require more complex behavior than
previously thought during this this era of spikes
and this raises challenging questions for core
modelers like myself um to try and explain uh what
what was going on during that time um
right at the bottom here is a reference
uh which for a paper which recently came out
describing uh what i presented today um with
a lot more detail and there's a reference here
right at the bottom for the code that i introduced
earlier that you that you can freely download and
run and that's it thank you for your attention
excellent thank you very much for that that was
a really interesting talk um we can all give
phil a a virtual uh round of applause uh through
zoom um and i'm sure there's gonna be an absolute
ton of questions because that was a really uh
uh personally find that really exciting talk so
um i will open the floor to questions and i can
see that uh andy begin as the first uh with his
hand hi phil hi andy nice talk um yeah i just
wanted um have you looked at relative errors
at all rather than applying an absolute
error allowing to scale with the actual
paleo intensity itself because that might
be a more realistic way of looking at it
uh that is a good question and we did think
very carefully about what errors to use
um in the paper i i didn't really want to go
too much into this in the talk uh just to keep
it snappy um but in the paper we do discuss
this at some length and we we tried using
uh what some of the authors um uh of of
the levantine data uh called an extended
uh intensity error um so we we we tried to look at
reasonable choices for yes for the intensity error
um and um well you can read about it in the
paper but basically it doesn't really change
our conclusion all right thanks thanks andy so
um kathy constable is the next with her hand up
yeah thanks uh i enjoyed your talk presentation
phil uh i just wanted to um raise a comment
you mentioned that uh chris and i in our papers
in 2017 2018 had difficulty finding spikes and
numerical dynamo models and i think that's
not a completely accurate characterization of
um what we what we said in those papers we did
actually find quite a number of spikes in dynamo
models whether they would meet the criteria that
you specify here um we haven't explicitly tested
but we did actually look for rapid changes in the
field and found quite a number in terms of the
field strength so i'd say it was still a fairly
open question as to whether we find these things
in the numerical simulations and there is
of course some difficulty in deciding what
the time scale they're occurring on would be yes
thank you that's a good point cathy um in one of
your studies with chris you also looked at the
localization of the spikes which is which is
a broad question that i've not really touched
upon here and as to whether whether the spikes are
seen only in one place or in a broader region and
i think that's that's another interesting question
yeah i think that uh inevitably if they're
coming from the core then they have to occur
over the broader region uh that's certainly
an interesting question for the helium
that the paleomagnetic data ought to be able
to address as well as the numerical simulations
yeah and the numerical simulations we
saw that the biggest changes in intensity
seem to occur at higher generally but at mid to
high latitudes rather than at low likelihoods
so you're kind of in between yes
yes okay thanks very much kathy um
we'll move on to gunther well first let me
thank you phil it was really good to talk
and i like it because it was very calm and
there was a assurance given and well thank you
it was very nice to listen to and i have a
question uh i mean you talk about spikes uh
why don't you talk about dips because it
looks like dips should work the same way
yes you're quite right maybe that we
should have inverse spikes or something yes
that's right so uh let me find a picture
so yes so you're quite right um i i guess
it's we're really following our lead from
the original papers that spotted this
very rapid intensity uh intensity change
um but you are but you are quite right in
that uh the the the concerns about getting
intensity increases also pertain to increasing
decreases as well because it's the same
physical process that you need to
explain uh both of both of these
we haven't we haven't actually looked at at uh
dips as you as you as you put it only the spikes
thank you cheers cheers um lisa
i have your hand up now i have a
thank you phil that was a
great talk i really liked it
i have a comment and a question the first
the comment and that is that you're using
the term spike and words matter so in a
different sense then we use the term spike
we defined a spike as being something with uh a
vadm higher than 160 zetta ammeter squared yeah
and that's not the way you're using it so i think
you should use a different term peak i don't know
you know some other word because it becomes very
confusing also if you start to use the word dip
note that dennis can't define that decrease in
paleo intensity many years ago and so you should
look into how he defined that because we end up
with too many words meaning too many different
things and nobody knows what
each other's talking about
the second uh point is a question and that
is in your bayesian model and you're allowing
um points to migrate which asian methods
allow you to do and i think that's powerful
the my question is that do you end up with an age
model for specimens that violates stratigraphy
because there are in some of these samples data
sets like uh the timna 30 and the megiddo one you
know you unless people were messing around and
taking things that are older and putting them
up in a younger strata you have a pretty good
constraint of age ordering and i'm just curious
if your model ends up violating that
or whether you take that into account
yeah it's a really good question uh lisa and
it's something that we were very conscious and
careful of to retain the stratigraphy of the of
the samples because we're we're well aware that
this is a really robust um finding from from
from the data and so in all all these models
wherever there are um age ordering uh these are
um these are taken into account by the modeling
okay so so when i say yeah you mentioned that the
the ages were perturbed they but only if they are
consistent with the struct with the stratification
constraints oh okay all right thank you
excellent thanks very much lisa and does
anybody else have a question to throw phil's way
nobody's going to drop the hands up i can
throw i'll let brenda brendan uh jump in
with his question first yeah so i guess uh
this is this is a very technical question
but um for your points like in your sort of
third and fourth spike around that area where
you might have like a bimodal distribution
that you end up with for the ages yeah how
how does like what does your sample of convergence
look like for that so how well does your how
old is your sample converge for things where
you've got like a bimodal distribution of ages
um so in in you you're right to uh to raise
the question of model convergence so is it
this is because it's all based on a numerical link
sampling numerical sampling strategy you have to
make sure you take enough samples that your your
distribution and any statistics derive from that
settle down and we're very careful to do that we
didn't look specifically at these bimodal times
but but we we basically ran the model for a very
large number of of iterations into the hundreds
of millions in order to to be absolutely
certain that everything was well converged
okay
thanks very much brandon does anybody
else um have questions for phil
uh cathy you've got your hand up again yeah
i i i since there's a dose of questions maybe
a chance to ask his but i want to know what you
think is going on yet two spikes within 30 years
of each other at 970 and 940 bc yeah yeah i kind
of i kind of left myself open for that cathy uh
um yeah as i said here this raises
challenging questions for core modelers
so it was hard enough to explain two spikes let
alone six um what is what is going on well if
if this is really what happened then in order
to get such a such a a quasi-periodic signal
the only things that i can think of that
might explain this is some kind of wave
wave propagation which has peaks and troughs
the other way of getting it would be to have
some some form of magnetic structure which is
sequentially or maybe a different sign so as
it emerges from the core you get an enhancement
and then a reduction in the intensity
followed by a further enhancement and
a reduction either way it's it's challenging to
think of how how this is uh how this how this
happened physically um so i don't really have any
good answers kathy it's a great question though
okay thank you thanks cathy so that sounds
like there's some sort of mexican wave in
the core that's giving us this bumpy behavior so
i guess actually kind of i'm just gonna jump jump
in before anybody else has a question i guess
that kind of leads nicely to what i'm thinking
in terms of of the detailed analyses that
you've done you know what what would you tell
the experimentalists the archaeomagnetists
in terms of of what you would like to see
from the data what time periods what um
information um should we be aiming for in an ideal
world assuming we can quite find those perfect
samples yeah well the uh the levantine region is
is amazingly well sampled uh so we've got yeah
taken at the fragment level at least there's loads
of loads of data which is fantastic a fantastic
resource i guess what we're missing here is
a comparison to data which are averaged over a
number of fragments so that one can be absolutely
certain of the values of intensity and also the
the error you that are attached um to them um
i guess that's the only thing like i can
say i i i know i know from the discussions
i've had with the various people who have
who've analyzed this data that that um
you're all very you know there's a lot of
certainty and a lot of confidence in in these
data points and i'm not i'm not questioning that
at all um i'm just trying to think of ways that
the conclusions derived from the fragment
level um data set might be also supported uh
by by um other data sets for
example by this average data set
thanks very much um we've
got two two more questions
and then we'll we'll draw it to a close so lisa
you're still on mute
so i was complimenting you um uh but um my
question is now um it seems to me that since each
our the at least the the group ron schar
eras and and i have our philosophy of
how to deal with the data has been changing
through time and we're trying to get better
and uh and there may be uh better ways to do it
now i think uh some of you would have heard of
uh brendan siege's um bayesian approach to to
coming up with what's the best what's the best
intensity for a particular fragment for example
but then to propagate those uncertainties that you
get or those uh credible intervals or um from a
consistent um better analysis all the way up into
the model that would be my vision of how we can
move forward so that because you have data from
many different labs different approaches different
methods and uh and so each one of these does have
there's different uncertainties built into
it and it seems to me i've been trying very
hard to get all of the data from our group into
the magic database with the measurement level
data and so that it could be treated in an in
an agnostic way and a consistent way and then
we would start from the measurements of
the actual fragments and then move up and
propagate the uncertainties up into your model
and proceed like that and it seems to me that um
that would overcome a lot of of uh argument about
you know is that particular data point any good or
not or was it curved or was it blah blah blah you
know all those arguments that we have every day
and it might be a way forward i'm just thinking
but we don't have some people haven't put their
data into the magic database yeah or but we
don't have access to the measurement level data
your buddy gale maybe eve
gallery could be convinced to put
it into some way and it could be
treated in a consistent way you know
um you you get what i mean right i do lisa
yeah i think it's a very good idea yeah
yeah so if don't yeah you can put your data into
the nash collection that would be great yeah yeah
it's not so easy i i tried no i know i know if
you need help we can help thank you appreciate
it in the blood that's where i actually said so
we'll move on uh is your question a quick one
yes it's quite quick we'll go for last one last
quick question and then we'll wrap it up thank you
so much for this nice presentation in this very
nice discussion i i am very surprised by the fact
that spikes disappear when we we deal with mean
side mean values i was wondering if you have an
explanation on that and uh i am also wondering
if are they are taking into account the single
fragment that if it really shows and correspond
to a real spike fast variation or it could be also
an um not real effect but like let's say uh
something that gets introduced by the error on
on the samples or maybe possible errors
of archaeologists or collections i'm not
referring only to the levantine collection that
is very well studied but in general and the last
point that i was wondering also when dealing with
such data and many times we take data from them
like geometry data said that we're actually
we have the mean values the site mini values
what do you suggest it's very close to the
breaks uh suggesting how can we plot the fragment
values when all other data to to use to
compare with our side beams thank you
um well i can certainly answer the first of
your your questions uh so you yeah you raise
an interesting point here about the data set uh
derived from group level averages of fragments uh
and so yes there is indeed only one spike
detected in the in in the top figure here
and you can see it it largely hinges upon one
single data point which is which is from turkey
and the reason why is a spike there i think uh
is because the error bars are quite tight um
the reason why there aren't other spikes is
simply because the uh the data don't require
the uh the other the other five um spikes mainly
because there aren't that many data points
um in the fragment level data set there are 139
uh data points here there are only 20 or 30.
uh and so really this what what what what you're
seeing here this rather simple change is really
a manifestation of the lack of data that we have
that can that can really uh describe rapid change
uh and as as more data points are added to this
collection uh the more spikes may become apparent
but at the moment this is the simplest model that
fits all the data and so the data don't require
anything more complicated so you suggest
to use fragment levels to plot out it well
there's a choice i mean you can either choose
a fragment level data and then you get more
obviously then you get loads of data which is
great and then uh and that that then shows that
you need six spikes or you go with the group
level data set uh and you and you just can
see that you just don't have that many data
and you can fit a simple model through them
excellent thanks very much i'm going to cut it
short there and we'll wrap up um today's seminar
thank you again to phil um for a uh another
fantastic presentation and just let me to
um so yeah thanks again phil it's a fantastic
presentation and another um really good um turnout
this week um just a little bit of housekeeping
before we uh before we go um we're going to
take another short break this is this is a kind
of a a one-off um presentation in between some
uh conferences we just had egu we'll have a
short break for the uh irm conference in santa fe
um and we'll be returning for the next magnets
on uh june 16th which will be given by uh andy
roberts from australia uh national university so
at this point we will actually be switching the
time um of the seminars so we're switching to a
time zone that's a little bit more friendly for
on the europe and eastern hemisphere region and so
our presentations are going to be um either 8 or 9
a.m um uk time and it's going to be a little bit
of flexibility to accommodate whether our speaker
is uh in in europe or whether they're in uh
eastern hemisphere i've got a couple more speakers
um lined up for for and seminars afterwards and
we'll confirm those uh details a little bit later
but we are um looking for more presenters um
in particular we really want to encourage um
early career scientists uh early career
researchers to to use magnets as a chance
to uh present some of their work because
right now it's it's not easy to go and visit
um all the big fancy conferences and magnets
is i think a really good friendly atmosphere um
for uh ecrs to to present their new research uh
and so and it's one of the reasons actually why
um we we set up this seminar series was to get
early career scientists recognized so that people
know who they are so please encourage um
any of your ecr or yourself if you are
an ecr here who's thinking about giving a
presentation so just reach out to to myself
uh or to anita and yeah just thank you everybody
for um joining this seminar thank you very much